Hello everyone.
大家好
I'm Rong Zhen.
我是荣振啊
Today, I'm showing my big face.
今天我把我的大脸露出来哈
Let's chat a bit.
跟大家聊一聊啊
I went to pick up my motorcycle today.
我今天去提摩托车了
Actually, the motorcycle was registered a few days ago.
其实摩托车前几天就注册好了
But it's only mentioned today.
但是今天才提啊
It's just that Beijing has been quite hot these past couple of days.
无非就是这两天北京比较热啊
And it's been raining intermittently.
又间断的下雨
People's desires tend to grow over time.
嗯人的欲望呢总是在增长
However, human capacity is limited.
而人的能力是有限的
Desires increase exponentially.
人的欲望呢是这个指数级的上升啊
I just got my car.
呃我刚提了车啊
I posted a few updates on my social media.
发了几条朋友圈
Someone asked, 'Rong, are you driving a sport bike or a street bike?'
就有人说荣哥你开的是仿赛还是街车呀
Are you riding an ADV?
你开的是ADV吗
Bro Rong, someone like you should at least get a 450cc or above.
荣哥你这样的人起码得买450cc以上啊
Bro Rong,
荣荣哥
with your financial means,
以你的财力
you could easily afford an ABV.
你买ABV没问题啊
Why did you only get a 125cc scooter?
你怎么只买一个125的小踏板啊
Ah, a lot of people started encouraging me to get something better,
啊很多人就开始就是开始怂恿我买更好的
a larger displacement,
更大的排量
a more powerful one. a more expensive car then I started to think should I buy a better, more powerful, and more expensive car? the other day I complained about the operations team giving me bad advice
更强的 更贵的车 然后我就开始琢磨诶 我是不是应该买一个更好更强大更贵的车啊 前两天我吐槽运营瞎给我出主意
which led to a decrease in my Power Up transactions
然后导致我的充电流水下降啊
but the most important reason isn't about what the operations team said
其实呢最重要的原因并不是敢那个运营怎么说
or whether what they said was right or wrong
或者运营说的这个东西到底对不对
it's that my heart has always been troubled by envy
而是我这颗嫉妒他人的心呢一直是有问题的
as I often say, comparison is the thief of joy
就是啊我常说comparison if the thief of joy啊
It's something that really takes away your joy.
就是比较让你夺走了快乐啊
A lot of the time, we say I have over 600,000 followers, almost 700,000.
很多的时候我们说我60多万粉丝快70万了
It's actually something to be really happy about.
其实是很值得高兴的一件事情啊
Because what I do is voice-overs.
因为我做的是口播啊
When it comes to voice-overs,
你要口播来讲
many people don't do it very well.
很多人做的并不是很好啊
Of course, there are now many people with over a million followers for voice-overs.
当然来讲口播有很多人现在都100多万粉丝了
They are better than me.
比我强
But let's face it, everyone's time to shine is different.
但是咱们说每个人啊火的时间不一样
Why are you in such a rush?
你为什么要那么着急呢
Various aspects within the industry During these guild gatherings You'll see many outstanding players Under the spotlight, they receive awards Their data is excellent Their performance keeps climbing
各种各样的这个行业内部的 这种这个行会集会的时候 你就会看到很多非常突出的选手 在聚光灯之下是人家拿奖 人家的数据非常好 人家的这个业绩增增的往上涨啊
You start to get anxious
你呢就开始着急
Oh, and you start to feel envious
哎你呢就开始嫉妒啊
I often say
我常说
that my mom only taught me to admire others
那我妈只教给我了这个羡慕别人
but not to envy them
不要嫉妒别人
but in reality
但实际上来讲呢
both my grandmother and my maternal grandmother were strong women
我的姥姥跟我的奶奶都是两个女强人
who really enjoyed comparing themselves to others
都特别喜欢跟别人比较
and feeling bad when they came up short
然后比别人差他就难受
and throughout their lives
然后这一生呢都会在这种竞争的思维下呢
they constantly pushed their children to compete
不断的激励自己的孩子
I want my child to be just as competitive as they are.
让自己的孩子呢也希望像他们一样争强好胜
But in reality, the kids tend to be more laid-back.
但其实孩子们却都比较平和
My parents were the type who didn’t seek conflict with others.
我父母都是那种与世无争的人啊
Of course, they were still quite ambitious.
当然来讲也比较要强
But this competitive mindset,
但这种竞争思维
to be honest, is a reflection of our country’s culture,
说实在的就是我们国家的这种啊
which emphasizes excellence and success.
文化优记主义啊
There's a drive to be the best.
要争第一
To be at the forefront.
要争先
But actually, this thing is meaningless.
但其实这个东西是没有意义的
You know?
你知道吗
It’s about being the first to compete.
就是你争先争第一
In the end, the platform wins.
最终胜利的是平台
Of course, that’s true. They manipulate you. And you generate better results. Naturally, everyone is part of the same interest group. But no matter what, You need to understand human desires are endless. You can't pursue infinite desires with a finite life.
哎肯定的啊 PUA你 然后你创造更好的业绩 当然来讲大家是一个利益共同体了 但是无论怎么样 你一定要明白 人的欲望是无止境的啊 你不能用有限的生命去追寻无限的欲望
At a certain point,
到了一定程度
you have to realize
你就要明白啊
the importance of steady and stable development.
要平稳的稳稳定的发展
To put it simply,
其实来讲的话
it's like riding a motorcycle.
摩托车就像这样似的
Actually, you can see Brother Rong driving a 125cc one.
实际上你看荣哥开个125的
Inside Beijing City
在北京城里边
I already feel it's incredibly fast
我已经觉得非常快了啊
I used to ride an electric scooter for 40 minutes
我之前要开40分钟的电瓶车
now it takes only 19 minutes by car
现在要开19分钟的车
I start from the western fourth ring of Beijing
我就从北京的西四环
and head straight to the northwest second ring
一直就杀到了这个西北二环啊
Of course, I have temporary plates these past two days
当然来讲我这两天是临牌
so I don't have to worry about the restricted areas
所以不用在意这禁行的问题
In a couple of days, I'll park at the northern fourth ring
过两天我就停到北四环了
Uh
呃
These past couple of days are my last chance to enjoy eating in Beijing
这两天就是我最后可以在北京城里边儿爽吃啊
During these days of riding the motorcycle
开这个摩托车的这几天呃
Because of buying gold coins
因为买金币嘛
Gold coins are still relatively scarce
金币现在仍然就是比较兵
Gold coins are good
金币好
For getting a Beijing A plate
上京A的话
It’s now 300,000
现在30万了啊
It used to be 400,000
以前都40万
It's now at 300,000.
现在30万了
So, if you can't get a license plate in Beijing,
所以啊在北京抽不到车牌的啊
and you have a motorcycle license,
有了摩托车驾照的啊
consider getting a Beijing A plate as soon as possible. Especially in the six central districts. So, once you get a car, you start thinking about a better one.
想上这个京A的这个朋友们尽快加紧啊 尤其是城六区的哈 所以这种事你说呢你一上了一个车 你就想更好的车
When you have a few hundred thousand followers,
你有了几10万粉丝
you start aiming for a million followers.
你就想要上百万的粉丝
You just want to be part of the BILIBILI UP100
你就想拿当百大
You just want to get the golden badge
你就想拿金色牌牌
Many people are talking about the current economic situation
很多人对现在的目前的经济形势呢
They are extremely pessimistic about it
非常非常的没有信心啊
I say, actually, all of you are talking about the economic downturn
我说其实你们所有的人都在说经济下行
Everyone is saying the economy is in bad shape now
都在说经济现在不行了啊
Who are you comparing yourself to
你是在跟谁比
First, you are comparing yourself to developed countries
首先你是在跟发达国家比啊
Are developed countries doing well themselves
发达国家现在自己行吗
Developed countries are struggling too these days.
发达国家现在自己也不行啊
Isn't that right?
对不对
Housing prices are dropping everywhere.
哪儿的房价都在降
Even in Vancouver, the housing prices have dropped.
温哥华的房价都降了
Vancouver, a place where global tycoons have been speculating in property.
温哥华这座全世界的富豪都去炒房的地方
Its housing prices have fallen as well.
他的房价都降了
Doesn't that indicate there's a problem with the global economy?
难道不能说明全球经济出了问题吗
And you keep bringing up the economic downturn.
而且你老拿经济下行
Compared to the years of economic growth in recent years.
这几年跟经济上行那几年比
That's just not right.
这就是不对的
You should compare it with the years when the economy was more stable.
你应该跟经济比较平稳的那几年比
Why don't you compare it with the year 776? Why don't you compare it with the year 75? Why can't you compare it with the years 83 and 84? The economy is definitely in better shape now than back then. Right? And there's more material abundance. You always compare it with the years when the economy was booming.
你干嘛不跟776年比啊 你干嘛不跟75年比啊 你干嘛不能跟8384年比一下 肯定经济现在经济情况比那时候好 对不对 那个物质也丰富 你老跟经济上行那几年比
It's like you're saying
你就好像在说啊
Brother Rong is now forty-one or forty-two
荣哥现在四十一四十二了
I don't have the same stamina as when I was 24
我现在体力没有我24的时候好
Isn't that obvious?
这不废话吗
You can't expect to have better stamina than when you were 24
你要体力比24岁岁数好
What did you eat, buddy?
你哥们儿你吃什么了
Buddy
哥们儿
What did you eat?
你吃什么了
Tell me, what did you actually eat?'
你告诉告诉我你到底吃什么了
Wow, it’s become so powerful all of a sudden
卧槽一下变得这么厉害
That’s intense
这么猛
This goes against the laws of nature
这不符合自然规律
Do you know that
你知道吗
You can’t keep comparing economic downturns with upturns
就是你不能老拿经济下行去跟经济上行
Which years are you talking about
那几年比
The economy was on the rise
经济之所以上行
Because of the large-scale infrastructure projects back then
因为那时候大基建
All those infrastructure projects hadn’t been completed yet
那个时候所有的这些基础设施没建造完
Of course he has his perks.
他当然有红利在了啊
If you want to boost the economy again now,
你想现在再让经济再上行一次
it's simple.
很简单
You tear down all the railways and skyscrapers across the country,
你把这全全全全国的这个铁路啊什么的
and rebuild them.
那个高楼全全全扒了
The economy will definitely rise again.
再建一遍
No problem.
那肯定还上行
It will rise again.
没问题
Still going up
还上行
The question is whether you can live an ordinary life
问题就是你能不能过普通日子
Whether you can live a normal life
你能不能过正常的日子
To enjoy a normal life in a moderately developed country Are you going hungry now? Or are you lacking necessities? Are you struggling to make ends meet? Are you, now? If you expect us not to buy a house
就是享受一个中等发达国家正常的日子 你现在是没得吃吗 你还是没得用吗 你现在是揭不开锅了吗 你现在是阿 如你让我们不买房
What are we supposed to do?
我们怎么办
Did you end up living under a bridge?
你住住桥洞了吗
Oh, are you living under a bridge?
啊你住桥洞了吗
You're currently staying in a public rental housing, right?
你现在住在公租房里边
Living under a bridge?
住桥洞了吗
Are you staying in that abandoned building?
住在那个烂尾楼里边了吗
I don't think so.
没有吧
So what are you complaining about?
所以你在抱怨什么
What are you barking about?
你在狗叫什么
I don't get it.
我不明白
Are your current conditions really better than they were back then?
就是你现在的这些状态难道就真的比当年好吗
Thinking back, it's been 20 years now.
当年啊现在一想当年20年前
Even 15 years ago, wow.
15年前哎呀
The economy was really good back then.
那时候经济真好啊
Is that what you thought back then?
你那时候是那么想的吗
You weren't thinking about things like Sudan Red,
你那时候想的不是什么苏丹红
Peacock Green, or the various Sanlu milk powder issues.
孔雀绿什么什么那个各种三鹿奶粉
Weren't those the things on your mind?
你不是想的是这些吗
Weren't you thinking about people dying here?
你想的不是这儿死人
There are fatalities there.
那儿死人
Is the disaster happening here, here?
这儿这儿出在那灾嘛
Is this what you were thinking?
你想的是这些吗
Back then, you also thought about doing your best, right?
你想的那时候你也是想因润尽润
Hurry up and run.
赶紧跑
Right?
对不对
Everything is fake.
什么东西都是假的
Nothing is real.
什么东西都不是真的
Nothing is appropriate.
什么东西都不合适的
There were issues everywhere.
然后哪哪都有问题
You were also full of complaints back then.
你那时候也是满腹牢骚啊
You talked to you about all these economic matters.
你跟你说所有这种经济这种事
To put it bluntly, it's just a BS thing. It's just make-believe. Do you know? If you can boost confidence, Everyone will have confidence, Everyone will think it can work out. This can be done. Everyone has lost confidence.
说白了就是一个MB的事情 就是一个make believe 你知道吗 就是你要是能激发信心 大家都有信心 大家都觉得这事儿能成 这事就能成 大家都没信心
When you encounter an issue,
遇到一个事儿啊
a security incident in a distant place might also turn bad.
老远的一个地方的一个治安案件也会不好了
You feel like it’s not going to work out.
你就觉得不行了
It’s not working anywhere in the country.
全国都不行了
When will things start to improve?
那你什么时候能行呢
Buddy,
哥们儿
an incident in a remote area
老远的偏远地区的一件事情
It's definitely very unfair.
他肯定很不公平
Just like the official explanation shows.
就跟这亮证解释的
It explains what's going on with him.
这亮证解他自己怎么么回事
Now, the official statement clarifies everything.
现在官方通报也知道是怎么回事
Why have you suddenly lost faith in everyone across the country?
怎么您一下对全国的人就都没信心了
Your confidence is pretty fragile, isn't it?
您这信心也够脆弱的啊
Just because of a village entrance blockage incident.
就出现这么一个堵村口的一事儿
Then you read the signs and make broad inferences.
然后你就见微知著啊
So, it's clear.
所以可以见得啊
It definitely won't work in the future
将来肯定是不行
I just don't understand where some people get their thinking from
我就不明白有些人那个思维到底是怎么来的啊
I ride a 125cc motorcycle
我骑着125的摩托
I wish I had a 450cc motorcycle
我就想450的摩托
And when the economy is in a downturn
然后我经济下行的时候
I think about how great it would be if it were booming
我就想着经济上行得多好
One peak and one trough
那一个波峰一个波谷
There's bound to be a huge difference
那差别能不大吗
Right?
对不对
The entire Y-axis is right there.
那整个Y轴都在那上面了
You should compare it with the usual, okay?
你应该跟平常去比好不好
You always go into stocks.
你老去股票里边
And you always compare yourself to those who have made a fortune. Who got rich overnight. Can you really be at peace with that? My buddy, First, you should compare yourself to the average. You need to understand this. There's always an up and a down. There are definitely people making money.
也是你老去比那些人家赚了大钱的 一夜暴富的 那你心里能平衡吗 我哥们 首先你就应该跟平均数去比二 你要明白 有上就有下 那肯定还有人挣钱呢
Right?
对不对
You should really consider changing your industry.
您应该考虑换个行业是真的
You should think about which industries are thriving now.
您应该考虑现在什么行业好做
Absolutely.
是真的
This is a fairly realistic situation.
这是一种比较真实的状态
Instead of trying to make it seem better.
而不是去make it believe
Always complaining
永远都在抱怨
I'm always thinking about this thing
永远都在想这个东西
What should I do?
我到底应该怎么办
And if this thing doesn't go well
然后这个东西一不好
it's the macro environment that's the issue
那就是大环境不行啊
a downturn in the economy
一不好就是经济下行
Now many people are paying the price for their own foolishness
现在很多人都为自己的愚蠢买了单
and they start blaming the economic downturn
然后就在那儿开始怪经济下行怎么着
But the macroeconomic environment has little to do with your personal gains and losses
经济大环境跟你个人得失其实关系并不大
really, it doesn't have much of an impact
真的关系并不大
You're not in the service industry.
你并不是做大众服务业的
What is the service industry?
什么叫大众服务业
What kind of work do you do?
就是你你你你干那那几行呢
I know what you do.
知道你干那几行
You interact with customers every day.
你天天接触客人
You see three or five customers a day.
一天接待三五个客人
When the economy takes a hit,
经济情况不好了
people spend less money on you.
大家给你花的钱就少了
That's why you might complain about the tough times.
所以你那种人你才有机会去抱怨大环境不好了
Actually, most people just stick to their own industry. But if your industry takes a downturn, you can definitely feel it. However, for many people, the connection between the overall economic environment and their industry is unclear. It doesn’t seem to have much of a connection at all. Then they start to panic at the slightest hint of trouble.
其实一般的人你还干你行业 如果你行业不好了 那你是能感觉到 可是很多人来讲的话 经济大环境跟他的行业有什么关系 跟没多大关系啊 然后就是听风就是雨
And they end up parroting what everyone else is saying.
然后就是人云亦云
Look, before all these official announcements come out,
你看所有的这些官方通报出来之前
Everyone's talking about it
大家都在那说
speculating all sorts of things
都在那猜测各种东西
So when there's no clear conclusion
所以有些东西就是没有定论的时候
and nothing can convince everyone
没有什么东西能说服大家的时候
rumors become the most effective
那谣言是最管用的
So if your rumor
所以如果你的谣言
Why do many people insist on doing IQ tests?
为什么很多人就是说要做智商测试呢
Because in the past, the internet was used by elites
因为以前的互联网都是一些精英
highly educated individuals
高知分子在用啊
In '97 and '98
97年九八年
In '99 and those years, it was like that
99年那几年是这样
Later on, it gradually became accessible to ordinary people
后来就变得慢慢的普通人也能上了
You had a computer
你有个电脑
As long as you could afford the internet fees
只要交得起网费
You could get online
你就上了
Nowadays
到现在来讲的话
You can get online with just a smartphone
你有个手机就能上了
Whether it's a Redmi or a budget phone
你有个红米也有个千元机
A machine costing five or six hundred yuan
五六百块钱的机器
allows you to go online
你也能上网
allows you to express yourself
你也能骂
allows you to cheer for your fandom
你也能说你也能为粉圈加油
Many things are like this
很多事儿就是这样
That's why there are more and more internet fools nowadays
所以现在互联网的傻子越来越多了
So, whether it's ordinary people or the intelligentsia
所以普通人高知啊
the intelligentsia are relatively easier to pacify
知识分子还比较好安抚你
They understand reason
讲道理啊
Just enforce the law clearly.
明法制就行
You're just a typical fool. No matter how you talk to him, it won't work. So, most people lack confidence. And most people are foolish. You need to understand this. Today, in China, those who have received higher education,
你一般的那种蠢货 你怎么去跟他说也不行 所以就显现的大部分人都没有信心 而大部分人是愚蠢的 你一定要明白一点 就是今天在中国受到高等教育的人
only make up 6.5% of the entire population.
只占全口全体人口的6.5%
You know, I have a college degree.
你说啊我大专啊
I'm a third-year student.
我三本
So you're also in that 6.5%
那你也在这6.5%里边
Most people don't have a basic understanding of science.
大部分人是没有基本的科学素养的
They don't understand statistics at all.
他根本就不懂什么统计学
or probability.
概率学
or psychology.
心理学
or social psychology.
社会心理学
They don't even know what social psychology is.
不知道什么叫社会心理学
When an infectious disease occurs, one bad event in one place can spread.
传染病就一个地方发生一件坏事以后
Other places will follow suit
其他地方也会跟着学
That's how it is
这就是这样
So after the first person at a university chose to jump
所以从高校第一个有人开始跳楼以后
Eventually, countless people at universities opted to jump
最后后来就有无数的人在高校选择跳楼
It's a bit of a barrier
有点障碍
A bit of pressure is just too much to bear
有点压力就受不了了
And they insist on taking their own lives in this manner
然后一定要选择这种方式轻生
This is a phenomenon in social psychology
这就是一种社会心理学
It's also related to epidemiology
传染病学
What do humanities disciplines do?
人文学科是干什么的
It's not just for leisure.
不是闲的
It's not about causing trouble for others.
没事让你给别人上眼药的
Studying humanities is about addressing the contradictions in human development.
学人文学科是解决人类发展当中的这些矛盾的
That's what humanities are all about.
这才是人文学科
The comprehensive significance of liberal arts lies in this.
文科的综合的意义就在于此啊
To resolve the contradictions in social development. This is crucial. So, we're back to the motorcycle issue. I bought the motorcycle for the joy it brings. Whose displacement am I comparing it to? People with high displacement bikes still die, you know.
要解决社会发展的矛盾 这是很关键的 所以又回到这个摩托车的问题 我买摩托车是为了快乐 排量我跟谁比呢 那排量高的人还有他妈死的呢
Right?
对不对
Is true happiness in economic development really a good thing?
经济发展的真正快乐就是好事儿吗
When the economy grows rapidly,
你经济发展快的时候
you haven’t even gotten on board yet.
你都没上车
Do you think rapid economic growth will benefit you?
你觉得经济发展快了以后跟你有什么好处
It will only widen the wealth gap between you and others.
你只会拉大你跟其他人的财富差距啊
Right?
对不对
Then I have this many followers,
然后我粉丝量有
At this point,
这个时候
Why didn’t I compare myself to those who have been banned for years?
我为什么没去跟那些被封禁了好几年的人
Why not?
去比呢
Why didn’t I compare myself to those with tens of thousands or even hundreds of thousands of followers,
为什么没跟那些粉丝十几万或者几万
Who have been doing this for years?
做了好几年的人去比呢
Why do I have to compare myself to the people ahead of me?
我为什么一定要跟我前面的人去比呢
I’m actually luckier than the people ahead of me.
我比我前面的人是比他们更幸运
Or maybe I'm just more capable
还是比他们更有能力还是怎么样
But the number of followers does reveal something
但是粉丝数能说明一定问题
But does that mean I'm not putting in effort
但是就证明我一定不努力吗
Does that mean I'm not good enough
就证明我一定不好吗
Does that mean I'm absolutely worthless
就证明我完完全全就是一个废物吗
Not necessarily
也不是啊
Why do you use others as a benchmark for yourself
为什么别人成了你研究自己的参照物
Why surpass the United States
为什么超过美国
Is the primary goal of our country's development
就是我们国家发展的第一要务
We just have to surpass it
就非得超过它
We just have to be stronger than him We just have to be the global hegemon The military hegemon In terms of military In terms of technology In terms of culture, we have to surpass him in everything Aren’t you tired? Is everyone prepared for the long-term role of being second?'
就非得比他强 就非得他是全球霸主 军事霸主 我们在军事上 科技上 文化上什么东西都得超过他 你累不累啊 大家有没有长期做老二的这种思想准备呢
Do we need to spend a long time preparing for development?
有没有很长时间我们要在发展当中做准备呢
Even if we surpass him later,
我们就算超过他了以后
Should we also keep a low profile and make a fortune?
那我们是不是也应该闷声发大财呢
Many issues are like this,
很多问题就是
Why do I have to reach one million followers?
我为什么一定要超过100万粉丝呢
Why do I have to buy a car with a 450cc engine?
我为什么一定要买450的这个排量的车呢
If I buy a car with a 450cc engine,
我买450的排量车
Will I have poor driving skills?
我会不会技术不好
Will I get into a fatal accident?
被撞死了
I got first place in this Mario race.
我拿这个比赛的第一马里奥比赛第一
But getting hit by a nuclear bomb as the winner isn’t exactly a good thing, is it?
结果第一名吃核弹是不是也是不好事
If we were to outperform the U.S. in every statistic,
我们要是处处统计数据都比美国强
wouldn’t the whole world start targeting us, making us the second?
是不是现在全世界都会针对我们当第二
Actually, there’s nothing wrong with that.
其实没什么不好啊
Being the nominal second,
当名义上的第二
while actually being the first, isn’t that perfect?
实际的第一不就完了吗
So once my follower count grows to a certain number,
所以我的粉丝量一旦增长到一定数目了
like reaching one million.
比如说增长到100万
Troubles started as I came along and spoke a lot.
我随之到来来来讲很多麻烦就开始
I became even more hesitant to speak up.
我就更不敢说话了
I won an award.
我拿了奖
After winning the BILIBILI UP100,
拿了百大以后
the possibility of me being banned would skyrocket.
那我封禁我的可能性就会直线上升
Because your words carry more weight now.
因为你的说话更有力度了
Did you ever think about it?
有没有想到
Actually, this figure is around seven or eight hundred thousand. This is the most wonderful time right now. You've hit one million two million you'll have meetings that never seem to end you have a 150cc
其实这七八十万上下 这种感觉是现在是最美妙的时候 你到了100万 200万 你的一些东西你就有开不完的会了 你有150cc
200cc
200cc
400cc
400cc
when you become a motorcyclist
你变成机车员的时候
you're not far from the end of your life
就离你的生命尽头就差不多了
your economy is on the rise every day
你天天都经济上行
What should we do?
那怎么办
The economy was booming back then.
那天天经济上行
Look at World War II.
你看二战的时候
Germany and Japan were experiencing economic growth every day.
德国日本那天天经济上行
The economy was doing great.
那经济好着呢
You were the locomotive of the economy.
那你是那个经济火车头
What about those people?
那那几个人吗
Right?
对不对
Do you feel like you're earning ten dollars?
你感觉到你挣十块钱的时候
So the rich made 1.1 million
那有钱人挣了110万呢
It’s better that no one does well
还不如大家都不好呢
It’s better if everyone is at an average level
还不如大家都是一个平均的一个水平
Nowadays, people find it hard to make money
现在大家觉得钱都难赚
So don’t always think about it
所以不要老想着哟
The past was really great
过去真好啊
Back in the 90s, people were already saying the past was better
90年代人就有人说过去真好
By 2000, people were saying the 90s were better
2000年就有人说90年代好
Back in 2001, people were saying things were better in the year 2000.
2001年的时候就有人说2000年的时候好
Now it's 2025,
现在2025年了
and some are saying things were better a decade ago.
就有人开始说10年前好了
But you didn't think so at the time, did you?
你当时没觉得好啊
Let me repeat that.
我再说一遍
Sudan Red,
苏丹红
Peacock Green,
孔雀绿
all sorts of colors,
各种各样的
My dad is Li Gang.
我爸是李刚
Was it good back then? You barely had time to worry about his affairs back then. All sorts of things. Wasn't the military equipment not as strong back then? This is the best era we have. The car priced at 125,000 has 800,000 views online.
那时候好吗 你那时候根本无暇顾及他的事 各种各样的事情 是不是那时候军备也没现在强 现在的时代就是最好的时代 125的车全网80万
With over 600,000 followers,
粉丝60多
670,000 followers,
67万
Brother Rong with 678,000 followers is the most candid now.
67.8万粉丝的荣哥是最能讲真话的时候
When we hit a million,
等100万的时候
I'll be talking nonsense.
我就该说屁话了啊
But don't worry,
但是大家放心
it'll all be good nonsense.
全是好屁
So at this point, it's crucial to understand the principle of moderation.
所以这个时候一定要明白中庸之道
What exactly is moderation?
中庸啊是什么
It's important to understand,
一定要明白
you must never be all show and no substance.
你一定不能中看不中用
Right?
对不对
The way of moderation is crucial.
中庸之道很重要
It means that extremes lead to their opposites.
就是物极必反
So many things develop positively,
所以很多事情发展到好
becoming the best in the world,
发展成世界第一了
performance improves,
排量上去了
follower count increases,
粉丝量上去了
but it might also mean that few can appreciate it.
有可能真是曲高和寡
or it might be lonely at the top.
有可能真是高处不胜寒
or it might not be as good as it seems.
有可能未必有
Now I feel even happier
现在觉得更加快乐
Sometimes you might find yourself unable to resist
有可能你就身不由己
That's just how things are in this world
这世界上的事情就是这样
This is the objective law of how things evolve
这就是事物发展的客观规律
So the premise of comparing yourself to others is that you believe they surpass you
所以你跟别人比较的前提是你认为别人超越你
Others are stronger than you They are happy But the question is, are they really happy? Isn't it true that someone's account with millions can be discarded at will? Just say you won't do it and that's it? An account with millions of followers He must have four sons at once
别人比你强 他就快乐 问题是他快乐吗 那不是有人几百万的账号说废就废 说不干就不干了吗 真正有了几百万的粉丝的账号 他就一定一胎生四个儿子
Then what happens
然后怎么怎么样
Would he be over the moon?
他就特别爽吗
Is it really that extreme?
真的是非常那样的吗
Of course, to be fair
当然来讲
Brother Rong isn't saying she must have children
荣哥也不是说姨胎非得生孩子
It's about having a bunch of sons
是生一生了一大堆儿子
I feel the same way.
我也是觉得
Having a baby is an incredibly tough experience.
生孩子这件事是非常非常难受的一件事啊
To put it plainly, in many cases,
说白了就很多的时候来讲
it might not make you feel all that great.
未必能让你感觉到多好
You might not truly enjoy the fruits of it.
你未必真正能享受到这种果实
You’re just seen as good in others' eyes.
你只是别人眼中的好
All those people I admire,
所有那些我羡慕的人
Do they even know I admire them?
他们知道我羡慕他们吗
Those who drive better cars than me
那些开的比我好的车的人
Do they know I envy them?
知道我羡慕他们吗
The ones driving luxury cars like the Cullinan or Maybach
就是开起来好车的那开库里南迈巴赫
Aren't there plenty of people driving Porsches and Ferraris?
开保时捷法拉利的人不是大有人在吗
Do they have three horns?
他们长了三个犄角
Don't they also have to go through birth, aging, illness, and death?
他们不是也得生老病死吗
So why do you have to drive a car with a large engine?
所以你为什么一定要开大排量的车
Why do you have to drive a luxury car?
为什么一定要开好车
Why does the number of followers have to increase?
为什么粉丝量一定要上升
Why do you have to attend Tsinghua or Peking University?
你为什么一定要上清北
Why do you have to be the best among your peers? Why does your why have to be longer than everyone else’s? Are you crazy? Are you okay? If you keep talking like that, you’re the one who’s crazy. Right? Why do you have to be better than others?
你为什么一定要是同龄人中的佼佼者 你的为什么必须比别人都长 有没有病啊 你你有没有病啊 你吊长你为准还有病呢 对不对 你为什么一定要比人强呢
That’s just the Chinese mindset.
就是中国人的思维
Sometimes I really don’t get it
我真是有时候闹不明白啊
We must be the best in the world
我们一定当世界第一啊
Our standards are higher than Japan’s
素质高于那个日本啊
Are the Japanese really that well-mannered?
日本人素质真的高吗
If they were more sophisticated, they wouldn’t engage in violence and looting
招高他就不烧杀抢掠了
Isn’t that right?
是不是啊
Our engineering technology must surpass Germany’s
我们的工程技术一定要高过德国啊
The Germans have a lot of experience in dealing with people
德国人在处理人这方面非常有经验
Right?
对不对啊
The economy is stronger than that of the U.S.
经济强于美国啊
The military power exceeds that of Russia.
那个武力值高于这个俄罗斯
Do you really think Russia's military power is high?
你真觉得俄罗斯武力高吗
Is the U.S. economy really that great?
啊经济美国真的就一定好吗
Sometimes, you know, things aren't as they seem.
唉嘶有的时候有些东西我跟你说啊
Living up to a great reputation can be tough.
盛名之下其实难付也很
Often, things aren't as good as they appear.
多的时候未必真正有那样好
You're comparing them in a very direct way.
你是实打实跟人比
They give you a fake presentation.
人家给你一假PPT
What are you going to do?
你怎么办啊
Buddy
哥们儿
You're always so pragmatic
你老那么务实
You're always chasing
你老那么追赶
That's the kind of mindset among Chinese people
就是中国人这种思想
In terms of military equipment
你在军备上
You can catch up with others in technology
科技上可以追赶别人
But there are many aspects of quality of life
但是生活品质上好多东西
You might not really need that much
你未必真用得了那么多
Buddy
哥们儿
Human desires are endless Don’t use endless desires to burn through your finite life and try to satisfy those endless desires Nature can’t bear it Your lifespan can’t bear it
人的欲望是无限的 不要用无限的欲望啊 拿你有限的生命去燃烧 然后去满足无限的欲望 那大自然承受不了的 你的寿命承受不了的
Your blessings can’t sustain such heights
你的福报承受不了那么高
125 is enough
125的就得了
Having a few hundred thousand followers
有个几10万粉丝
Getting over half a million is really impressive
超过50万就已经很了不起了
Dude
哥们儿
To be honest
说实在的
Now you have a country that's the second largest economy in the world
你现在能有这么一个全球经济第二的国家
You're better off than being born in
你比生在什么不
Bina a soul
Bina a soul
There's no way Burundi can compare to South India
还有什么布隆迪比申论南印度那强多了
Dude, based on the current birth rate
哥们按现在的出生人口比例
If you were to be reincarnated
你再投胎一次
you'd likely be born in India
大概率会成为印度人
so being born in China
所以你生在中国
isn't that great?
你还不觉得好吗
I'm not saying everything is perfect in China
我不是说啊中国什么都好
China is fantastic in many ways
中国什么都特棒呀
I think coming to China is particularly great
我觉得来中国特别好
I'm someone like Flav
我是弗拉夫之类的
I'm not that kind of person either
我也不是那样的人
But let's be honest
但是咱们说实在的
You shouldn't always compare economic downturn data with economic upturn data
你不要老拿经济下行的数据说跟经济上行的比
You keep bringing up Sister Lotus
你老拿芙蓉姐姐
Comparing her with Lin, oh
拿凤姐跟那个林林林哎呀
I've forgotten who else
我都忘了是谁了
But anyway, comparing her with those beautiful ones
反正就跟那几个漂亮的比
It's not necessary
你没必要啊
Why compare your weakest with others' strongest
为什么要用最弱的比人最强的
It's like the story of Tian Ji's horse racing
田忌赛马啊
You're really out of your mind. Is it because you always compare your weaknesses with others' strengths? You never really think about it. What are your strengths? Sometimes I don't think about it either. I always feel that my self-media isn't doing well.
你这简直有病 是不是你老拿短板跟长的比 你从来就不好好想想 你自己的长处是在什么地方 我有的时候就不好好想想 我老觉得哦自媒体做的不好
But I scored 8.5 in IELTS.
那雅思还8.5呢
My buddy got 29 in TOEFL.
哥们儿托托福29呢
Who's better than you in English exams?
你英文考试里边谁比你强
Now you think that...
你现在觉得啊
Others have better French literature than me.
人家有法文学的比我好的
But didn't you know French 15 years ago?
那你不是15年前你就会法语了吗
They only got good at it recently.
人家不是现在才好了吗
If you study a bit more,
是不是你再学一学
You might be even better.
你可能比他还好呢
But why do you have to be better than him?
但是你为什么一定要比他好
Can't you just use it and be done with it?
你能用不就完了吗
He needs to use French now.
他现在需要用法语
So his French is good.
所以他法语好
You don't need to use French now.
你现在又不用法语
Why does your French have to be better than others?
为什么法语一定要比别人强
Let me ask you something.
就是我问你一句话
Why do I have to be better than others?
为什么我一定要比别人强
Why does my... have to be bigger than others?
我为什么吊一定要比别人大
Why can't I have hair loss?
为什么我头发一定不能脱发
Why do I have to be thinner than others?
为什么我一定要比别人瘦
Why do I have to be more handsome than others?
为什么我一定要长得比别人帅
Why do I have to have more money than others?
为什么我钱一定要比别人多
Why does my house have to be bigger than others?
为什么我房子一定要比别人大
Why does the engine displacement have to be high?
为什么我们说排量一定要高
Why do I have so many followers?
为什么我粉丝量非常大
Why do I have to live in the top country in the world?
为什么我非得生活在全球第一的国家
I must be crazy.
我有病啊
Am I crazy?
是不是有病啊
Is there something wrong with my brain?
我是不是自己脑子出了问题啊
I have to go to Tsinghua or Peking University. I have to attend a key high school. I have to be the top of my grade. Being second is unacceptable. If I have 100 points, I have to score 100. If I score 99, My dad would scold me. Isn't that crazy? Is there something wrong with my mindset?
我在一个学校就必须得是清北 我必须得上重点高中 我必须得拿年级第一 年级第二都不行 我有100分 我就得考100分 考99 我爸都骂我 是不是他妈有病啊 是不是我的心态出了问题
Am I psychologically disturbed?
我心里变态了
Is there something wrong with my mental state?
是不是我心理有问题
That's why I'm not happy.
所以导致我不快乐
Is that the problem?
是不是就是这个问题
So, buddy, think it through.
所以哥们想明白点
It's a mindset issue.
就是自己心态问题
Just an engine displacement,
就一个摩托排量
Why do you always compare?
你都跟人比你比啊
Always comparing who's bigger,
天天比谁吊大
Always comparing who has more hair,
天天比谁头发多
Always comparing who can stay young longer,
天天比谁能保持养颜
Bro, I'm already on a downhill slope.
哥们儿已经开始走下坡路了
Aging is a natural law, okay?
生老病死自然规律好吗
Is it normal to have more hair than 24 people now?
你现在头发比24人多正常吗
Of course, in some places,
当然你像有的地方
The hair is definitely more than the others, right?
那毛肯定比二所尔特人多多了对吧
Of course, you can't see that part anyway.
当然那东西你长得也看不见啊
Right?
对不对
So don't compare yourself with others.
所以不要跟别人比较
Let me say it again,
再说一次
Comparison is the thief of joy.
比较是快乐的小偷
Never compare yourself with others.
千万不要跟人比
You'll be happy as long as you don't compare.
你只要不比你就快乐